Guide to the Cornell University calendar collection, 1902-2005.
Cornell University calendar collection,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Cornell University calendar collection, 1902-2005.
48-1-241
Cornell University.
3.6 cubic ft.
Printed material.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Illustrated annual calendars: some listing social, educational, athletic, and artistic events on campus, and dates of the university's operation and instruction. Some include appointment and schedule information from previous owners.
1993 Cornell calendar, with drawings by Ioana Schipor, 1992.
Academic year 1956-57 - 1960-61 calendars annotated with campus events by Ronald Demer, member of the Class of 1959.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Illustrated annual calendars: some listing social, educational, athletic, and artistic events on campus, and dates of the university's operation and instruction. Some include appointment and schedule information from previous owners.
1993 Cornell calendar, with drawings by Ioana Schipor, 1992.
Academic year 1956-57 - 1960-61 calendars annotated with campus events by Ronald Demer, member of the Class of 1959.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Cornell University.; Schipor, Ioana.; Demer, Ronald.; Cornell University; Cornell University. Class of 1959; Cornell University
Form and Genre Terms:
Calendars.; Calendars
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Includes collection #48-1-2690.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Chronological list of calendars
Series II. Duplicates
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Chronological list of calendars
  - Cornell Calendar 1902, 1902 (Box 1)
    "Epic verse" (including a poem, titled "Prologue," on the opening page and the four poems beginning with each season ["In Winter," "In Spring," etc.]) and the full page illustrations on the cover and for each month are by J.K. Fraser ('97); the pages are "[f]urther embellished by the work of Jay van Everen, '99 and W.D. Straight, '01;" copyright belongs to The Ezra Press, 1902; this calendar is the gift of "Miss M.J. Hull."
  - Cornell University Calendar 1906, 1906 (Box 1)
    Cover, printed on a kind of thin, laminated wood, featuring the Cornell University seal with Ezra Cornell's profile in the center; a label on the back of the cover reads: "Gift of J.A. Skidmore in memory / of Charles Fleet Scudder '11, and / Marguerite Arthur Scudder Celley / May 16, 1972;" features BW photographs of the campus and the sports teams with titles underneath; includes a photograph of "President Schurman Dedicating Goldwin Smith Hall."
  - 1908 Cornell Calendar, 1908 (Box 1)
    Calendar leaves have no binding; features BW photographs of the campus for each month with descriptions underneath, including one photograph of "President Shurman at 'Inspection,'" in which he is talking to several police officers.
  - Cornell Calendar 1909, 1909 (Box 1)
    Cover features a color illustration of an half-naked man leaning against a stump in the green woods with a pen in his right-hand and his eyes staring thoughtfully into an easel we cannot see, giving the illustration a very sylvan, "dales of Arcady" atmosphere--a vision of the Arts Quad appears in a silver frame in the center; features BW photographs of the campus for each month with titles underneath.
  - 1909 Cornell Calendar, 1909 (Box 1)
    Features BW photographs for each month but without titles or descriptions; the photographs are printed onto scrapbook paper and roughly trimmed, then printed in reproduction form to give the calendar a very "cosy" appearance; additionally, the calendar months are handwritten for similar effect.
  - A Calendar from Cornell for 1910, 1910 (Box 1)
    Cover features a BW photograph of the profile of Ezra Cornell; calendar leaves have no binding; features BW photographs of the campus for the months with titles underneath.
  - Cornell 1911, 1911 (Box 1)
    The calendar is "Donated / by Luther L. Emerson A.B. 1928 / property of Isabel Dolbier Emerson (Whitson) / my aunt (Class of 1902)" (handwritten on back of cover); features BW photographs for each month with descriptions on back of calendar; there is a (mendable) tear on the back of the calendar.
  - Cornell MCMXII Calendar, 1912 (Box 1)
    "Gift of Henry Cape Jr." handwritten in pencil (and almost illegible) on top left corner of cover; features colored-in photographs for the months and includes titles underneath.
  - Cornell 1912, 1912 (Box 1)
    The cover depicts a color reproduction of "Senior Singing," an oil painting designed and painted by Christian Midjo; features BW photographs of the campus for each month with descriptions on back of calendar.
  - The Cornell Calendar for 1912, 1912 (Box 1)
    Cover features the illustration of an open book with words reading: "I / would found / an / institution / where / any person / can find / instruction / in any study;" features BW photograhs for the months and includes titles emphasizing the dramatic weather of Ithaca (i.e. for the months of January and February, "The Gloom and Snow of January--Central Avenue").
  - 1913 Cornell, 1913 (Box 1)
    Black leather cover with a color Cornell shield and a color illustration of McGraw Tower on the front; features a colored-in photograph of Taughannock Falls and BW photographs of various scenes about campus with titles underneath.
  - 1913 [with Cornell Univ. Seal], 1913 (Box 1)
    Leather cover with colored-in photograph of McGraw Tower and Uris Library printed onto the leather; features BW photographs of the Cornell sports teams and various scenes about campus, each with titles underneath; additionally includes a BW photograph of Jacob Gould Shurman, then president of Cornell University.
  - 1913 Cornell, 1913 (Box 1)
    Red leather cover with a colored-in illustration of McGraw Tower and Uris library; features BW photographs of the campus for each month but without titles or descriptions.
  - The Cornell Calendar 1914, 1914 (Box 10)
    Calendar is OVERSIZED. The cover features a colored-in photograph of the "Goldwin Smith Entrance" in a golden frame; features BW (and blue) photographs of the gorges and buildings on campus for each month (with titles underneath).
  - Cornell University, 1914 (Box 1)
    The calendar is missing a bottom flap which unfolds to reveal the days of the months i.e. the actual calendar; includes 15 leaves of really stunning BW photography depicting the winter weather of Ithaca, Cornell's campus, students between class or out sporting and (presumably in June) graduating, etc.; descriptions of the photographs on back of calendar.
  - MCMXIV Cornell Calendar, 1914 (Box 1)
    In oversized envelope; features BW photographs for each month with titles at the bottom; curiously, the calendar lists the dates of the moon cycles (i.e. "First Quarter," "Full Moon," "Last Quarter," and "New Moon") above or below each month.
  - Cornell 1914, 1914 (Box 1)
    Leather cover with Cornell University shield imprinted; features BW photographs of the capmus throughout with titles underneath.
  - Cornell University Calendar, 1915 (Box 1)
    Calendar intended for faculty, "Showing Univeristy Holidays and Faculty Meetings / 1915 - 1916;" calendar is one single board of thick stock, folded in half, with a pin-hole at the top.
  - 1915 Cornell University, 1915 (Box 1)
    Cover looks as if coffee were spilled across it; however, the calendar has the bottom flap which unfolds to reveal the days of the months i.e. the actual calendar; the cover was designed by Christian Midjo; includes 15 leaves of really stunning BW photography depicting the winter weather of Ithaca, Cornell's campus, students between class or out sporting and (presumably in June) graduating, etc.; descriptions of the photographs on back of calendar.
  - Cornell 1916 Calendar, 1916 (Box 1)
    Calendar opens like an envelope with the bottom flap folding down to show the months and the days; the top flap folds up to show 12 leaves, each with a colored-in photograph depicting a part of the Cornell campus with titles underneath.
  - 1916 Cornell Calendar, 1916 (Box 1)
    Leather cover with metallic-verdigris-apparent Cornell University seal glued (?) to front; a small metallic pin depicting a coat of arms and a number "15" (a Cornell class of '15 pin [?]) is attached to the lower left corner; features BW photographs of the various Cornell 1915 sports teams, including the varsity and freshman teams and individual photos of the teams' captains; "Made by The Chas. L. Willard Co., New York, for J.H. Allen, Jr. and L.J. Rummell."
  - Cornell University 1916, 1916 (Box 1)
    Features BW photographs for each month with descriptions on back of calendar; the month of October features "First touchdown by Captain Barrett, in First Game of Football played on Schoellkopf Field, Gettysburg-Cornell, September 28, 1915" in addition to a full page of three photographs documenting the "Harvard-Cornell [football game] at Cambridge, Oct. 23, 1915," the score ending "Harvard, 0: Cornell, 10."
  - 1917 Cornell University, 1917 (Box 1)
    The cover depicts a color reproduction of an oil painting of Goldwin Smith Hall and the A.D. White statue--the faint signature of "C.M.S. Midjo" (Christian Midjo[?]) is in the lower right corner; a card on the back of the cover quotes the poem, "Andrew Dickson White," by Albert W. Smith, reading: "Here 'mid the fair fulfillment of his dream / His statue broods above the busy ways;" features BW photographs for each month with descriptions beneath each photograph; a photograph of "Ex-President Taft" and "President Schurman" is featured for April; half of the month of January is missing; the entire month of December is missing.
  - Cornell University 1918 Calendar, 1918 (Box 2)
    Cover features a colored-in photograph of the Cornell campus and Cayuga Lake faintly in the background; features many exceptional colored-in photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus; the bottom flap folds down to reveal the days of the month i.e. the actual calendar.
  - Cornell 1918, 1918 (Box 2)
    The cover features a BW photograph of the Cornell R.O.T.C. marching through the Arts Quad; a handwritten note in the top left corner of the cover reads: "Hubbell / #1955;" features BW photographs throughout with a few of the Cornell R.O.T.C. (including titles underneath).
  - 1919 Cornell University, 1919 (Box 2)
    Calendar includes a mail envelope from the publisher, "Troy's Cornell / Art Calendar / 1919," with an addressee of "Dr. D. Schott;" the cover features a BW photograph of the Ezra Cornell statue in the Cornell Arts Quad; the cover has some handwritten measurements at the bottom (but is in otherwise better condition than the duplicate); a bottom flap unfolds to to reveal the days of the months i.e. the actual calendar; there are many BW photographs (with titles underneath) depicting the Cornell R.O.T.C. training about campus.
  - 1920 Cornell University, 1920 (Box 2)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student life; one photograph (in July) documents the "Unveiling of the Ezra Cornell Statue;" various lines of poetry "accompanying the pictures of this calendar with four exceptions are from the Semi-centennial Ode by Martin W. Sampson."
  - Cornell 1921, 1921 (Box 2)
    A colored-in photograph of McGraw Tower is center on the cover; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student life and sports.
  - Cornell 1921, 1921 (Box 2)
    Black leather cover with the Cornell shield imprinted bottom-center; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of various Cornell campus buildings; curiously, the calendar lists the dates of the moon cycles (i.e. "First Quarter," "Full Moon," "Last Quarter," and "New Moon") above or below each month.
  - The Cornell Class Reunions, 1922 (Box 2)
    Begins with a cover letter by "Foster M. Coffin, Alumni Representative," imploring the Cornell alumni to return for the reunions; a small calendar published to advertise the 18 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1872 to 1919) all to be held on June 16th through the 18th; an uncredited cartoon illustration on the top of the calendar depicts a crowd of alumni carrying signs and bags with their graduation year (e.g. "1872," "1912," etc.) and walking toward McGraw Tower; the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June.
  - 1922 Cornell, 1922 (Box 2)
    The cover, beneath a BW photograph of McGraw Tower, includes a quote by Albert W. Smith, reading, "Hail Thou in Majesty, Cornell, on Guard Forever on the Height;" features BW photographs (with titles underneath) depicting the campus and student life and sports; two photographs of interest (in October) are: 1) "Mr. George F. Baker Laying the Corner-stone of the New Chemistry Building--His Gift to Cornell University;" and, 2) "The Inauguration. The New President Livingston Farrand and Acting President A.W. Smith."
  - 1922 Cornell, 1922 (Box 2)
    The brown leather cover is very weathered but depicts the head of Athena (?) between two lighted lamps and above the Cornell shield; the months are paired on each leaf (e.g. "January and February" on the first leaf and on the next leaf "March and April") with untitled BW photographs of various Cornell campus buildings.
  - 1923 Cornell University, 1923 (Box 2)
    The leaves for the months of January and March are folded over; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student life and sports, including a (small) photograph (in July) of what appears to be mostly if not all men swimming in the Fall Creek Gorge and another (small) photograph (in September) of "maidens" retrieving arrows from a target during an archery class (with a clever quote below, reading, "More merciful than Cupid, who ne'er / withdraws a dart once sped," written by Albert W. Smith).
  - 1923 Cornell Calendar of Winter and Spring Events and the Reunions, 1923 (Box 2)
    This calendar includes a cover letter by "Foster M. Coffin, Alumni Representative," imploring the Cornell alumni to return for the reunions; a small calendar published to advertise the 21 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1873 to 1921) all to be held on June 15th through the 17th; the drawing (of the Arts Quad at the calendar's top) is by "J. Andr Smith '02" and the lettering is by "John T. Parson '99;" the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June with a reminder-note to sign up for the class reunion; the following months of July through December are all on the back of the calendar.
  - Cornell 1924, 1924 (Box 2)
    Cover features a heavily sepia-colored photograph of McGraw Tower printed onto delicate tissue paper; features sepia-colored photographs (with titles underneath) depicting the campus and student life, including two photographs of the moonlight on the campus in April and two photographs of "The Mud Rush" in May; exceptional photographs in this calendar.
  - Cornell 1924, 1924 (Box 2)
    The cover BW photograph (a view of McGraw Tower between the pillars at Goldwin Smith Hall) is loose from the calendar (but inside the manila folder); there is a handwritten note in pencil with the catalog number (#48/1/241) in the top right corner; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student life; one photograph (in March) depicts three "Bronze Statues [The Boy with a Thorn; Discus Thrower; and, Praying Boy] from the large collection in the Museum of Archeology representing the best of Greek sculpture."
  - 1924 Cornell Calendar of Winter and Spring Events and the Reunions, 1924 (Box 2)
    A small calendar published to advertise the 22 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1869 to 1922) all to be held on June 13th through the 15th; the drawing (of the Arts Quad at the calendar's top) is by "J. Andr Smith '02" and the lettering is by "John T. Parson '99;" the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June with a reminder-note to sign up for the class reunion and urges alumni "to make yourself responsible for the presence of at least three old cronies;" the following months of July through December are all on the back of the calendar.
  - 1925 Cornell, 1925 (Box 2)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) mostly of the academic buildings on campus in addition to several photographs of student life and sports; includes (in August) an illustration of Willard Straight Hall "by the Architects, Messrs. Delano and Aldritch."
  - Cornell 1925, 1925 (Box 2)
    Includes sepia-toned photographs of the campus, the student life and sports, and several of the Cornell R.O.T.C. training; two (albeit small) photographs of the "The Mud Battle" are in May.
  - Cornell 1926, 1926 (Box 2)
    A colored-in photograph of the Arts Quad is on the center of the cover; sepia-toned photographs (with titles underneath) for each month depict campus, student life and sports; two photographs for the month of January document astronomical phenomena: 1) "Total Eclipse of the Sun from Cornell, January 24, 1925;" and, 2) "The Corona of the Eclipse;" the faces and bodies of people in several of the photos appear to have been "touched-up" with pencil in the pre-publishing process.
  - 1926 Cornell, 1926 (Box 2)
    A BW photograph of the Arts Quad is center on the cover; there is a handwritten note in pencil with the catalog number (#48/1/241) in the top right corner; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student goings-on; one photograph of note is "President Farrand's Commencement Address, June 15, 1925" (in June); additionally, one photograph (in December) features "Professor Kinkeldey, Professor Harold Smith, and the Advanced Choir of Sage Chapel."
  - 1926 Cornell Calendar of Winter and Spring Events and the Reunions, 1926 (Box 2)
    A small calendar published to advertise the 19 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1871 to 1924) all to be held on June 11th through the 13th; the drawing (of the Arts Quad at the calendar's top) is by "J. Andr Smith '02" and the lettering is by "John T. Parson '99;" the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June with a reminder-note to sign up for the class reunion and the promise that "June 1926 should surpass all previous celebrations;" the following months of July through December are all on the back of the calendar.
  - Cornell 1927, 1927 (Box 2)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); the excellent photograph of McGraw Tower, featured on the cover in sepia-tone for the "Cornell 1924" calendar, is also on display for the month of September in better scale (and with its illumination technique revealed: a searchlight!).
  - Cornell 1927, 1927 (Box 2)
    A colored-in photograph of McGraw Tower is on the center of the cover; BW photographs (with titles underneath) for each month depict campus, student life and sports, including one photograph wherein "President Farrand decorates the prize-winning cadets of the R.O.T.C." (for the month of April).
  - 1928 Cornell, 1928 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the campus and student goings-on; "J.F. Anderson" and "N.G. Wright" are featured in May for track and field events; in the photograph for June, "Dexter Kimball" is seen leading the "Senior Singing on the Steps of Goldwin Smith Hall;" in the photograph for December, "Commander Byrd pays tribute to the memory of Ross Gilmore Marvin, Cornell, 1905, at Sage Chapel."
  - Cornell 1928, 1928 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); the photograph of "Ezra Cornell on a Winter Night" (in January) and the one of "Goldwin Smith Hall at Night" (in December) are of exceptional and dramatic quality (the January photograph, at its bottom right corner, has a handwritten note, reading: "N5543").
  - Cornell Class Reunions, 1928 (Box 3)
    A small calendar published to advertise the 17 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1873 to 1926) all to be held on June 15th through the 17th; the six BW illustrations throughout are uncredited; the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June; unlike the previous "Reunion" calendars, this one lacks the reminder-note to sign up for reunions (it seems likely that it was not issued).
  - Cornell MCMXXIX, 1929 (Box 3)
    The cover features a colored-in photograph of the A.D. White statue and the Arts Quad with McGraw Tower in the background; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and major events (e.g. sports and commencement).
  - Cornell 1929, 1929 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement).
  - Cornell 1930, 1930 (Box 3)
  - 1930 Cornell Calendar of Winter and Spring Events and Reunions, 1930 (Box 3)
    A small calendar published to advertise the 22 different Cornell class reunions (ranging from the years 1869 to 1928) all to be held on June 11th through the 13th; the drawing (of the Arts Quad at the calendar's top) is by "J. Andr Smith '02" and the lettering is by "L.S. Fuertes '29;" the calendar features individual leaves for the months of January through June with the following months of July through December are all on the back of the calendar; this calendar, like the 1928 edition, lacks the reminder-note.
  - Cornell 1930, 1930 (Box 3)
    Cover features a color photograph of the Ezra Cornell statue; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); the photograph "Beacham's Band Makes Its Debut at the Niagra Game" in November is of interest.
  - Cornell 1931, 1931 (Box 3)
    Cover features a colored-in photograph of the Cornell War Memorial; features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); there is a small "Architects Sketch of Myron Taylor Hall" for the month of August.
  - Cornell 1931, 1931 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); also includes three aerial-view photographs of the campus (with one of "Schoellkopf Field during Princeton Game" in November).
  - Cornell 1932, 1932 (Box 10)
    Calendar is OVERSIZED. Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and student-life; the photograph for June features the popular swimming hole in Beebe Lake under the bridge with swimmers, male and female.
  - Cornell 1932, 1932 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); the photograph of "The Library from the War Memorial Archway" in October is particularly pleasant; also includes two aerial-view photographs of the campus.
  - Cornell 1933, 1933 (Box 10)
    Calendar is OVERSIZED. Features exceptional BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and student-life; the photographs for June document the commencement of the previous year and includes a great photograph of "The Commencement Procession Wind[ing] Its Way Around Schoellkopf Field."
  - Cornell 1933, 1933 (Box 3)
    Features BW photographs (with titles underneath) of the Cornell campus and several events (e.g. sports and commencement); also includes two aerial-view photographs of the campus.
  - Cornell 1934, 1934 (Box 3)